Goodbye Bafana is a history, drama film directed by Bille August.
The true story of a white South African racist whose life was profoundly
altered by the black prisoner he guarded for twenty years.
The prisoner's name was Nelson Mandela.
James Gregory, played by Joseph Fiennes.
Nelson Mandela, played by Dennis Haysbert.
Gloria Gregory, played by Diane Kruger.
Brett Gregory, played by Shiloh Henderson.
Major Pieter Jordaan, played by Patrick Lyster.
Jimmy Kruger, played by Norman Anstey.
Goodbye Bafana, or The Color of Freedom (US), is a 2007 drama film, directed by Bille August, about the relationship between Nelson Mandela (Dennis Haysbert) and
James Gregory (Joseph Fiennes), his censor officer and prison guard, based on Gregory's book Goodbye Bafana: Nelson Mandela, My Prisoner, My Friend.
The film also explores the relationship of James Gregory and his wife as
their life changes while Mandela is under Gregory's watch.
Bafana means 'boys'.
Gregory lived on a farm and had a black friend when he was a
child, which explains his ability  to speak Xhosa.
The film explores themes of escape, prison cell,
jail guard, south africa, apartheid.
The tone is emotional.